Guide to the Pennsylvania Environmental Council Collection, 1970-1998 AIS.1999.18
ULS Archives & Special Collections
- Environmental Activities/Projects, 1970-1992; V.
  - Green Resources Wilkes-Barre Project, 1992 (Map-case 9, Folder 42)
- Department of Environmental Resources, 1981-1993; VI.
  The Pennsylvania Environmental Council (PEC) contacted the Department of Environmental Resources to receive information regarding particular environmental legislation. This series contains the information received by the PEC and is arranged subject specific to their particular interests on environmental issues. The organization gathered this information to further their knowledge on the legislative issues and to ensure processes were being carried out properly.
  - DER, 1988-1992 (Map-case 9, Folder 43)
  - DER, 1981-1988 (Map-case 9, Folder 44)
  - DER, 1988-1989 (Map-case 9, Folder 45)
  - Advisory Council Low Level Radioactive Waste, 1988-1989 (Map-case 9, Folder 46)
  - Advisory Council Low Level Radioactive Waste, 1989 (Map-case 9, Folder 47)
  - Advisory Council Low Level Radioactive Waste, 1988 (Box 20, Folder 1)
  - Advisory Council Low Level Radioactive Waste, 1985-1988 (Box 20, Folder 2)
  - Advisory Council Low Level Radioactive Waste, 1987-1989 (Box 20, Folder 3)
  - Advisory Council Low Level Radioactive Waste, 1989 (Box 20, Folder 4)
  - Advisory Council Low Level Radioactive Waste, 1986-1988 (Box 20, Folder 5)
  - Advisory Council Low-Level Radioactive Waste, 1989 (Box 20, Folder 6)
  - Advisory Council Low Level Radioactive Waste, 1987 (Box 20, Folder 7)
  - Advisory Council Low Level Radioactive Waste, 1986-1988 (Box 20, Folder 8)
  - Advisory Council Low Level Radioactive Waste, 1986-1988 (Box 20, Folder 9)
  - Advisory Council Low Level Radioactive Waste, 1988 (Box 20, Folder 10)
  - Advisory Council Low Level Radioactive Waste, 1988-1989 (Box 20, Folder 11)
  - Advisory Council Low Level Radioactive Waste, 1988 (Box 20, Folder 12)
  - Advisory Council Management Review, 1986 (Box 20, Folder 13)
  - Advisory Council Management Review, 1986 (Box 20, Folder 14)
  - Advisory Council-Office of Surface Mining, 1985-1993 (Box 20, Folder 15)
  - Advisory Council-Office of Surface Mining, 1987-1990 (Box 20, Folder 16)
  - Advisory Council-Office of Surface Mining, 1988 (Box 20, Folder 17)
  - Advisory Council PennVest, 1987-1991 (Box 20, Folder 18)
  - Advisory Council PennVest, 1988 (Box 20, Folder 19)
  - Advisory Council Radon Advisory, 1985-1986 (Box 20, Folder 20)
  - Advisory Council Scenic Rivers, 1988 (Box 20, Folder 21)
  - Advisory Council Scenic Rivers, 1984-1990 (Box 21, Folder 1)
  - Advisory Council Sewage Advisory, 1986-1988 (Box 21, Folder 2)
  - Advisory Council Sewage Advisory, 1987-1989 (Box 21, Folder 3)
  - Advisory Council Sewage Advisory, 1987-1988 (Box 21, Folder 4)
  - Advisory Council Storage Tanks, 1988-1989 (Box 21, Folder 5)
  - Advisory Council Wetlands, 1989 (Box 21, Folder 6)
  - Advisory Council Wetlands, 1989 (Box 21, Folder 7)
  - Advisory Council Wetlands, 1986, 1989 (Box 21, Folder 8)
  - Advisory Council Wetlands, 1989 (Box 21, Folder 9)
  - Advisory Council Wetlands, 1986-1989 (Box 21, Folder 10)
  - Advisory Council Wetlands, 1989 (Box 21, Folder 11)
  - Citizens Roundtable, 1986-1988 (Box 21, Folder 12)
  - Citizens Roundtable, 1987 (Box 21, Folder 13)
- Handbooks/Policies, 1974-1990; VII.
  The collection includes two large handbooks created by the PEC: the Environmental Management Handbook and the Growth Management Handbook. The Environmental Management Handbook goes into detail about dealing with environmental issues. The environmental issues included in the handbook are those that the PEC has collected large amounts of information about (water, waste, insecticides, etc). The environmental management handbook also includes information about environmental issues and local government and the comprehensive planning required to promote these issues.
  The second handbook included in the collection is the Growth Management Handbook. This handbook is a guide to build better communities in an attempt to protect the Pennsylvania countryside. The Growth Management handbook includes advice on how each Pennsylvania municipality can implement a plan to successfully fulfill to steps the PEC has suggested.
  - Environmental Management Handbook Minutes, 1977 (Box 21, Folder 14)
  - Environmental Management Handbook, 1974, 1975, 1977, 1978 (Box 21, Folder 15)
  - Environmental Management Handbook, 1974, 1975, 1977, 1978 (Box 21, Folder 16)
  - Environmental Management Handbook, 1974, 1975, 1977, 1978 (Box 21, Folder 17)
  - Environmental Management Handbook, 1974, 1975, 1977, 1978 (Box 21, Folder 18)
  - Growth Management Handbook Original Unedited Drafts, 1990 (Box 21, Folder 19)
  - Growth Management Handbook Brown Art, 1990 (Box 21, Folder 19)
  - Growth Management Handbook Notes, 1990 (Box 21, Folder 20)
  - Growth Management Handbook Drafts, 1990 (Box 21, Folder 21)
  - Growth Management Handbook Drafts, 1990 (Box 21, Folder 22)
- Publications, 1971-1998; VIII.
  The Pennsylvania Environmental Council (PEC) produces numerous publications throughout the year regarding various environmental issues. The first of these publications is Forum, a newsletter produced by PEC three times per year that includes information on environmental policies, projects, and events. The second form of publication produced by PEC is News and Views, which contains information similar to Forum. Also included in the News and Views publications are summaries of conferences and events as well as legislative processes. This series also contains publications made by PEC on Pennsylvania's environmental laws and guidelines.
  - PEC Conference Report, 1988 (Box 22, Folder 1)
  - PEC Environmental Bulletin, 1992 (Box 22, Folder 2)
  - Forum Volume 17, 1987 (Box 22, Folder 3)
  - Forum Volume 18 and 19, 1989-1990 (Box 22, Folder 4)
  - Forum Volume 20, 1991 (Box 22, Folder 5)
  - Forum Volume 21, 1992 (Box 22, Folder 6)
  - Forum Volume 22, 1993-1994 (Box 22, Folder 7)
  - Forum Volume 23 and 24, 1995 (Box 22, Folder 8)
  - Forum Volume 25 and 26, 1996-1997 (Box 22, Folder 9)
  - Forum Volume 26 and 27, 1997-1998 (Box 22, Folder 10)
  - News and Views Volume 1, 1971 (Box 22, Folder 11)
  - News and Views Volume 2, 1972 (Box 22, Folder 12)
  - News and Views Volume 3, 1973 (Box 22, Folder 13)
  - News and Views Volume 4, 1974 (Box 22, Folder 14)
  - News and Views Volume 5, 1975 (Box 22, Folder 14)
  - News and Views Volume 6, 1976 (Box 22, Folder 15)
  - News and Views Volume 7, 1977 (Box 22, Folder 17)
  - News and Views Volume 8, 1978 (Box 22, Folder 18)
  - News and Views Volume 9, 1979 (Box 22, Folder 19)
  - News and Views Volume 10, 1980 (Box 22, Folder 20)
  - News and Views Volume 11 and 12, 1981 and 1982 (Box 22, Folder 21)
  - News and Views Volume 13, 1983 (Box 22, Folder 22)
  - News and Views Volume 14 and 15, 1984, 1985 (Box 22, Folder 23)
  - News and Views Volume 16, 1986 (Box 22, Folder 24)
  - Publications Miscellaneous, 1976 (Box 22, Folder 25)
  - Rules and Regulations 3rd Edition, 1978 (Box 22, Folder 26)
  - Rules and Regulations 4th Edition, 1980 (Box 22, Folder 27)
  - Rules and Regulations 5th Edition, 1981 (Box 22, Folder 28)
  - Rules and Regulations 6th Edition with Supplement, 1983 (Box 22, Folder 29)
  - Rules and Regulations Pamphlets, undated (Box 22, Folder 30)
  - Special Report-Managing Municipal Waste, 1986 (Box 22, Folder 31)
- Videotapes, IX.; 11 boxes
  Added to the collection in August 2013, these 354 videotapes were shot between 1994-2001 as part of the Three Rivers Environmental Awards, sponsored by the Pennsylvania Environmental Council and Duquesne Light Company. They depict a broad spectrum of environmental topics, including community projects, regional history, recreation, environmental science, as well as scenic footage of the Western Pennsylvania environment not found elsewhere. The collection consists of raw footage as well as edited tape in a variety of video formats, including high definition. This material was used at the annual Three Rivers Environmental Awards dinner which showcased the work of as many as 30 local projects each year as well as several segments of an environmental theme. A complete inventory of the video is available in the archives.